{"tossups": [{"question": "This man liberated Bulgaria from 400 years of Ottoman rule following a successful siege of Pleven. He employed Dmitri Milyutin to open army recruitment to all social classes, and he encouraged the new <em>zemstvo</em> system of local government. Loris-Melikov\u2019s work with this leader to establish a parliament was thwarted when this leader was assassinated by the People\u2019s Will in St. Petersburg. For ten points, name this Russian tsar who emancipated the serfs.", "answer": "<b> Alexander II</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Kelcy Warren serves as the CEO sponsoring this project, which was prohibited from utilizing space under Lake Oahe by the Army Corps of Engineers in December 2016. Shailene Woodley was arrested while protesting this project, which Energy Transfer Partners intends to run to Illinois from the Bakken fields. For ten points, name this pipeline that, controversially, is to run through the Standing Rock Indian Reservation.", "answer": "<b> Dakota Access Pipeline</b> (or<b> DAPL</b>; accept<b> Bakken Pipeline</b> before Bakken is read; prompt on descriptions of \u201cthe pipeline going through Standing Rock,\u201d etc., before the key words are mentioned)", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "This scientist is often credited with inventing the anchor escapement used in pendulum clocks. Isaac Newton\u2019s quote \u201cIf I have seen further it is by standing on the shoulder of giants\u201d was probably a jab at this scientist\u2019s short height. He wrote about his use of microscopes in his book<em> Micrographia</em>, and his namesake law can be stated as restoring force is proportional to displacement. For ten points, name this British scientist who coined the term \u201ccell.\u201d", "answer": "Robert<b> Hooke</b>", "metadata": "Science - Physics"}, {"question": "Description acceptable. A group advocating this action modeled its activities on the Bryce Group in Britain. Edward House drafted a plan calling for this action, which relied upon the work of the Phillimore Committee. William Borah and Henry Cabot Lodge opposed this action, citing their disapproval of Article Ten of a certain proposed covenant. For ten points, name this action, never taken despite the efforts of President Woodrow Wilson, which doomed a certain international body to irrelevance.", "answer": "the<b> U</b>nited<b> S</b>tates<b> join</b>ing the<b> League</b> of Nations (accept equivalent descriptions; prompt on answers related to the US signing the Treaty of Versailles)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This leader\u2019s father launched the 1970 Corrective Revolution. A revolution against this leader began after a boy was arrested for political graffiti in Daraa. To stop the Southern Front and Army of Conquest, this Ba\u2019athist leader allegedly ordered his air force to use barrel bombs in an ongoing civil war. This leader brokered a ceasefire with Vladimir Putin shortly after recapturing Aleppo in December 2016. For ten points, name the current president of Syria.", "answer": "Bashar al-<b>Assad</b> Page 1", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "\u201d John Sherman names an act that required the U.S. government to purchase this commodity. The Bland-Allison Act mandated that the government create coins from, for ten points, what metal, which was once traded at a sixteen to one ratio for gold?", "answer": "<b> silver</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "During this battle, one side was saved by timely naval support from the<em> Lexington</em> and<em> Tyler</em>. Nathan Bedford Forrest led a charge along the Corinth Road in this battle, which turned with the arrival of Don Buell\u2019s Army of the Ohio. Albert Sidney Johnston was killed early in this battle as his troops attacked the Hornet\u2019s Nest in an attempt to push Union forces away from Pittsburgh Landing. For ten points, name this 1862 victory in Tennessee for Ulysses S. Grant.", "answer": "Battle of<b> Shiloh</b> (accept Battle of<b> Pittsburg Landing</b> before mentioned) Page 2", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This man gained power by exiling the chancellor William Longchamp. He gained the territories of Brittany and Normandy after the Treaty of Le Goulet with Philip II Augustus, but lost them after his defeat at the Battle of Bouvines. After this man tried to appoint an Archbishop of Canterbury, Innocent III excommunicated him. For ten points, name this brother of Richard the Lionheart who, after being confronted by English nobles at Runnymede, signed the Magna Carta.", "answer": "King<b> John</b> (accept<b> John</b> Lackland or<b> John</b> I)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "This city\u2019s self-described \u201coldest neighborhood\u201d of Corktown contains its abandoned eighteen-story Central Station. The Ambassador Bridge spans this city\u2019s namesake river, connecting it to Windsor. A riot centered on this city\u2019s 12th Street was quelled when George Romney called in the National Guard in summer 1967. The Renaissance Center, home to GM, was built near the Chrysler Freeway in, for ten points, what Michigan city, home to America\u2019s \u201cBig Three\u201d automakers?", "answer": "<b> Detroit</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This man decided not to contest an election after Estes Kefauver won the New Hampshire primary. This man used Turnip Day as an opportunity to attack the Republican majorities in the 80th Congress. This man, who ordered the integration of the armed forces, suffered in popularity later for his nationalization of the steel mills during the Korean War. For ten points, name this president who was not defeated by Dewey during the 1948 Presidential election.", "answer": "Harry S.<b> Truman</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "A difficult sonata for this instrument by Giuseppe Tartini is nicknamed \u201cDevil\u2019s Trill.\u201d J.S. Bach wrote a set of sonatas and partitas as solos for this instrument, which was made in Cremona by families like Guarneri and Amati. For ten points, name this highest-pitched string instrument to be manufactured by Antonio Stradivari.", "answer": "<b> violin</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "While defending this government, Jaroslaw Dombrowski supposedly asked \u201cdo they still think me a traitor?\u201d as he died. Gustave Courbet fled to Switzerland after advocating the destruction of the Vend\u02c6ome Column during this government\u2019s tenure. Supporters of this government were shot at the Federalists\u2019 Wall in P`ere Lachaise [pair la-shez] during the Bloody Week, in which Marshal MacMahon restored control for Adolphe Thiers [tee-air]. For ten points, name this revolutionary socialist government, formed after the Franco-Prussian War in the French capital.", "answer": "<b> Paris Commune</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "This writer\u2019s opposition to the collection of indemnities by William Ament after the Boxer Rebellion prompted him to write an essay \u201cTo the Person Sitting in Darkness.\u201d This author made a chronicle of a westward stagecoach journey with his brother Orion. This author of<em> Roughing It</em> also wrote about his early years as an apprentice to a steamboat captain in<em> Life on the Mississippi</em>, in which he explained the genesis of his pen name. For ten points, name this author, born Samuel Langhorne Clemens, famous for his<em> Adventures of Tom Sawyer</em>.", "answer": "Mark<b> Twain</b> (accept Samuel Langhorne<b> Clemens</b> before read)", "metadata": "Literature - American Literature - Misc Literature"}, {}, {"question": "This man tried to force Richard Corbin to pay for gunpowder that had been seized by Lord Dunmore. Thanks to a speech noting that \u201cCaesar had his Brutus; Charles I his Cromwell,\u201d this man was accused of treason towards George III. In another speech, this man asked \u201cis life so dear, or peace so sweet, as to be purchased at the price of chains and liberty?\u201d For ten points, name this Virginian Founding Father who declared \u201cGive me liberty or give me death!\u201d", "answer": "Patrick<b> Henry</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This man was threatened by a rival expedition led by Francisco de Garay. He invaded Honduras to defeat his rebellious lieutenant Crist\u00b4obal the Old. This man was attacked by his rivals Diego Velazquez and Bishop Fonseca in the Council of the Indies. This man burned his ships after landing at modern Veracruz and allied with the people of Tlaxcala [t\u2019lahsh-kah-lah]. He captured Montezuma II in his capital of Tenochtitlan and created the Viceroyalty of New Spain. For ten points, name this conquistador who conquered the Aztec Empire.", "answer": "Hernan<b> Cortes</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>This man\u2019s exile to Europe was reported by Lauren Lyman. His expedition to aid China after a flood is documented by the book</b><em><b> North to the Orient</b></em><b>. This man, who proposed a neutrality pact with Germany and supported the (+) America First movement, had his son kidnapped by Bruno Hauptmann in the \u201cCrime of the Century.\u201d In 1927, this man won the Orteig Prize for his (*)</b> journey from Roosevelt Field to Le Bourget Field. For ten points, name this American aviator who undertook the first non-stop trans-Atlantic flight.", "answer": "Charles<b> Lindbergh</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>Just before leaving for this event, Jed Bartlett teaches the Secretary of Agriculture how to pick a Chief of Staff in a Season One episode of</b><em><b> The West Wing</b></em><b> titled \u201cHe Shall, from Time to Time...\u201d. That episode title references Article (+) 2, Section 3 of the Constitution, detailing the need for these events. Kiefer Sutherland\u2019s character becomes President because he is the (*)</b> \u201cdesignated survivor\u201d of this event in a 2016 ABC drama. For ten points, name this annual political speech given by the President to a joint session of Congress.", "answer": "<b> State of the Union</b> address (or speech, etc.; prompt on descriptions of Presidential speeches)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>A legend about this battle notes that the losing king was saved by an angel who turned him to marble. The Hungarian Orban designed the Basilica and Dardanelles guns for use</b> <b>in this battle in an attempt to breach the (+)</b> <b>Theodosian Walls. The winning side in this</b> <b>battle used a series of greased logs to transport ships across the Golden Horn. (*)</b> Mehmed II was victorious in, for ten points, what 1453 siege in which the Ottomans captured the capital of the Byzantine Empire, renaming it Istanbul?", "answer": "1453 Siege (or Battle, etc.) of<b> Constantinople</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>This country was harshly criticized by the EU after the appointees to its Constitutional Tribunal were abruptly changed by the newly-elected Law and Justice Party in 2015.</b> <b>The perpetrator of the 2016 Berlin Christmas Market attack (+)</b> <b>hijacked and killed a</b> <b>truck driver from this country. During October 2016, thousands of women in this country participated in the \u201cBlack Monday\u201d protests against a proposed total (*) </b> ban on abortion. For ten points, name this predominantly Catholic country led by Andrzej [andr-zhay] Duda from Warsaw.", "answer": "<b> Poland</b> (or<b> Polska</b>)", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "For ten points, name this revolt of native American tribes in the Great Lakes region, led by an Ottawa chief.", "answer": "<b> Pontiac</b>\u2019s Rebellion (or War, Uprising, etc.) Page 9", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>One leader of this country packed the head of a rival in ice so that he could communicate with it. Black dogs in this country were hunted down after the disgraced Clement Barbot</b> <b>was thought to have transfigured; Barbot was later caught in person by the (+)</b> <b>Tonton</b> <b>Macoute police. In 2011, when former president Jean-Claude Duvalier returned to this poorest country in the Western Hemisphere, he was arrested on corruption charges upon his arrival in (*)</b> Port-au-Prince. For ten points, name this nation that shares the island of Hispaniola with the Dominican Republic.", "answer": "<b> Haiti</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>The Academic Legion toppled a government in this empire when Franz von Pillersdorf failed to repeal censorship laws. This empire lost possession of Lombardy in the Treaty of</b> <b>Villafranca during the Italian Wars of Independence. Following (+)</b> <b>Francis I\u2019s defeat at</b> <b>Austerlitz and the ensuing Treaty of Pressburg, the Holy Roman Empire was effectively reorganized as this empire. In 1867, this empire entered into the (*)</b> Ausgleich dual-monarchy under Franz Joseph I. For ten points, name this empire that merged with Hungary in the 19th century.", "answer": "<b> Austria</b>n Empire (do not accept Austria-Hungary)  (1) <b>This case originated in part from a marriage performed by Lawrence Taliaferro</b> <b>[\u201dTolliver\u201d]. The original defendant in this case was Irene Emerson, widow of an</b> <b>army doctor who moved from Missouri to (+)</b> <b>Wisconsin. The ruling in this case</b> <b>differentiated between national and state citizenship and used the Privileges and</b> <b>Immunities Clause to determine that the plaintiff could not (*) </b> sue. Roger Taney [TAW-ney] ruled that the Missouri Compromise was unconstitutional in, for ten points, what highly controversial 1857 Supreme Court case that ruled slaves could not be U.S. citizens? ANSWER:<b> Dred Scott</b> v. San(d)ford", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}